<bibdata type="standard" schema-version="v1.2.8">
  <fetched>2024-11-17</fetched>
  <title type="title-intro" format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">Geographic information</title>
  <title type="title-main" format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">Schema for moving features</title>
  <title type="main" format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">Geographic information - Schema for moving features</title>
  <title type="title-intro" format="text/plain" language="fr" script="Latn">Information géographique</title>
  <title type="title-main" format="text/plain" language="fr" script="Latn">Schéma des entités mobiles</title>
  <title type="main" format="text/plain" language="fr" script="Latn">Information géographique - Schéma des entités mobiles</title>
  <uri type="src">https://www.iso.org/standard/41445.html</uri>
  <uri type="obp">https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/en/#!iso:std:41445:en</uri>
  <uri type="rss">https://www.iso.org/contents/data/standard/04/14/41445.detail.rss</uri>
  <docidentifier type="ISO" primary="true">ISO 19141</docidentifier>
  <docidentifier type="iso-reference">ISO 19141(E)</docidentifier>
  <docidentifier type="URN">urn:iso:std:iso:19141:stage-90.93</docidentifier>
  <docnumber>19141</docnumber>
  <contributor>
    <role type="publisher"/>
    <organization>
      <name>International Organization for Standardization</name>
      <abbreviation>ISO</abbreviation>
      <uri>www.iso.org</uri>
    </organization>
  </contributor>
  <edition>1</edition>
  <language>en</language>
  <language>fr</language>
  <script>Latn</script>
  <status>
    <stage>90</stage>
    <substage>93</substage>
  </status>
  <copyright>
    <from>2008</from>
    <owner>
      <organization>
        <name>ISO</name>
      </organization>
    </owner>
  </copyright>
  <relation type="instanceOf">
    <bibitem type="standard">
      <fetched>2024-11-17</fetched>
      <title type="title-intro" format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">Geographic information</title>
      <title type="title-main" format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">Schema for moving features</title>
      <title type="main" format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">Geographic information - Schema for moving features</title>
      <title type="title-intro" format="text/plain" language="fr" script="Latn">Information géographique</title>
      <title type="title-main" format="text/plain" language="fr" script="Latn">Schéma des entités mobiles</title>
      <title type="main" format="text/plain" language="fr" script="Latn">Information géographique - Schéma des entités mobiles</title>
      <uri type="src">https://www.iso.org/standard/41445.html</uri>
      <uri type="obp">https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/en/#!iso:std:41445:en</uri>
      <uri type="rss">https://www.iso.org/contents/data/standard/04/14/41445.detail.rss</uri>
      <docidentifier type="ISO" primary="true">ISO 19141:2008</docidentifier>
      <docidentifier type="iso-reference">ISO 19141:2008(E)</docidentifier>
      <docidentifier type="URN">urn:iso:std:iso:19141:stage-90.93</docidentifier>
      <docnumber>19141</docnumber>
      <date type="published">
        <on>2008-06</on>
      </date>
      <contributor>
        <role type="publisher"/>
        <organization>
          <name>International Organization for Standardization</name>
          <abbreviation>ISO</abbreviation>
          <uri>www.iso.org</uri>
        </organization>
      </contributor>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <language>en</language>
      <language>fr</language>
      <script>Latn</script>
      <abstract format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">ISO 19141:2008 defines a method to describe the geometry of a feature that moves as a rigid body. Such movement has the following characteristics.
- The feature moves within any domain composed of spatial objects as specified in ISO 19107.
- The feature may move along a planned route, but it may deviate from the planned route.
- Motion may be influenced by physical forces, such as orbital, gravitational, or inertial forces.
- Motion of a feature may influence or be influenced by other features, for example:

The moving feature might follow a predefined route (e.g. road), perhaps part of a network, and might change routes at known points (e.g. bus stops, waypoints).
Two or more moving features may be “pulled” together or pushed apart (e.g. an airplane will be refuelled during flight, a predator detects and tracks a prey, refugee groups join forces).
Two or more moving features may be constrained to maintain a given spatial relationship for some period (e.g. tractor and trailer, convoy).


ISO 19141:2008 does not address other types of change to the feature. Examples of changes that are not adressed include the following:
- The deformation of features.
- The succession of either features or their associations.
- The change of non-spatial attributes of features.
- The feature's geometric representation cannot be embedded in a geometric complex that contains the geometric representations of other features, since this would require the other features' representations to be updated as the feature moves.
Because ISO 19141:2008 is concerned with the geometric description of feature movement, it does not specify a mechanism for describing feature motion in terms of geographic identifiers. This is done, in part, in ISO 19133.</abstract>
      <abstract format="text/plain" language="fr" script="Latn">L'ISO 19141:2008 définit une méthode permettant de décrire la géométrie d'une entité mobile se déplaçant comme un corps rigide. Ce type de déplacement présente les caractéristiques suivantes.
- L'entité se déplace à l'intérieur d'un domaine composé d'objets spatiaux conformément à l'ISO 19107.
- L'entité peut se déplacer le long d'un itinéraire planifié, mais elle peut s'en écarter.
- Le mouvement peut être influencé par les forces physiques, telles que les forces orbitale, de gravitation ou d'inertie.
- Le mouvement d'une entité peut influencer d'autres entités ou être influencé par elles, par exemple comme suit.

L'entité mobile peut suivre un itinéraire prédéfini (tel qu'une route), pouvant faire partie d'un réseau, et peut modifier les itinéraires au niveau de points clés (par exemple arrêts de bus, points de cheminement).
Deux ou plusieurs entités mobiles peuvent être «tirées» ensemble ou poussées séparément (par exemple un avion ravitaillé en vol, un prédateur ayant repéré et suivant sa proie, des groupes de réfugiés unissant leurs forces).
Deux entités mobiles ou davantage peuvent être contraintes de conserver une relation spatiale donnée pendant une certaine période (par exemple tracteur et semi-remorque, convoi).


L'ISO 19141:2008 ne régit pas d'autres types de changement en matière d'entité. Les changements non abordés sont par exemple les suivants.
- La déformation des entités.
- La succession de chaque entité ou leurs associations.
- La modification des attributs non spatiaux des entités.
- La représentation géométrique de l'entité ne peut pas être présente dans un complexe géométrique comportant des représentations géométriques d'autres entités, car cela impliquerait une mise à jour des représentations des autres entités en même temps que le déplacement de l'entité.
Étant donné que l'ISO 19141:2008 couvre la description géométrique du déplacement de l'entité, elle ne spécifie pas un mécanisme consistant à décrire le mouvement des entités en termes d'identificateurs géographiques. Ce mécanisme est présenté en partie dans l'ISO 19133.</abstract>
      <status>
        <stage>90</stage>
        <substage>93</substage>
      </status>
      <copyright>
        <from>2008</from>
        <owner>
          <organization>
            <name>ISO</name>
          </organization>
        </owner>
      </copyright>
      <place>Geneva</place>
    </bibitem>
  </relation>
  <place>Geneva</place>
  <ext schema-version="v1.0.0">
    <doctype>international-standard</doctype>
    <editorialgroup>
      <technical-committee number="211" type="TC" identifier="ISO/TC 211">Geographic information/Geomatics</technical-committee>
    </editorialgroup>
    <ics>
      <code>35.240.70</code>
      <text>IT applications in science</text>
    </ics>
    <structuredidentifier type="ISO">
      <project-number>ISO 19141</project-number>
    </structuredidentifier>
  </ext>
</bibdata>